on this video we are going to learn
about a design pattern that is
incredibly helpful easy to apply and
that will make your code Shine the
pattern we will learn about on this
video is from the structural category if
you don't know what that means I suggest
you check out our previous video where
we introduced the concept of design
patterns and learned about their
categories today's pattern is the facade
pattern just like the facade of a
building hides its complex structure and
details the facade pattern in software
design is used when we need to make a
complex system simpler and easier for
the user to interact with when using the
facade pattern we create a class that
has a set of methods that are
straightforward and easy to use these
methods interact with the system's
internal components handling the complex
operations and offering the user an
easier way to interact with the system
for example let's pretend that we have a
smart home a home where the lights
thermostat security and TV are all
connected whenever we leave the house we
have to remember to turn off the air con
dim the lights arm the alarm system and
turn off the TV one action requires many
other small actions that sounds like the
perfect use case for a facade let's
create a smart home facade class first
when the class is initialized in the
Constructor it is going to initialize
the subsystems it will be controlling
lights aircon security and television
when we leave our house we want to turn
off all the lights switch off the air
conditioning and start the security
system when we return home we want to
light up the entrance turn on the air
conditioning and stop the security
system if we decided to watch a movie we
would like to lower the brightness in
the living room change the TV to the
movie channel and turn on the air
conditioning before heading to sleep we
turn off all the lights switch off the
air conditioning and start the security
system again now our smart home has a
facade and as you can see thanks to the
facade pattern we can hide all the
complexity and we can get an easy to use
interface where all we have to do is
call the methods we need and forget
about what goes on behind the scenes for
a more realistic example you can use the
facade pattern like I do when you are
fetching from or sending a lot of data
to an API instead of having a bunch of
fetch courses spread throughout your
application which can be difficult to
maintain and understand you can hide all
these operations behind a single facade
we first create an API facade class that
will have a base URL property passed on
the construction then we can create a
method to send or get data to and from
our API the post method is going to send
the post requests and the get method is
going to just do normal fetch get
requests now we can use this facade by
first setting the base URL and then call
in the method with the pads and data you
could go one step further and create
methods for every API action like here
where we now have the get users and
create user method so when we use the
facade it looks even better and that's
it for this video I hope you found it
useful and I hope you can see how
helpful and easy to use the facade
pattern is if you like this video and
comment below that you want to learn
more the next video I'll make will be
about behavioral design patterns so let
me know in the comments if that is
something you would like to see if you
like the way I explain things and you
will like to learn things like
JavaScript python react react native go
dark flutter among many many others for
absolutely free all you have to do is
click the link below to join any of our
many free courses that you can take
right now for absolutely free with me
click the link below and I will see you
there
see you on the next one bye
thank you